<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts from a Wall Street developer</title>
    <description>A blog about C++, with an emphasis on low-latency, performance measurements and system programming.
</description>
    <link>http://david-grs.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://david-grs.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 21:56:45 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 21:56:45 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why you should use Boost.MultiIndex (Part I)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Although Boost.MultiIndex is a pretty old library — introduced in Boost 1.32, released in 2004 — I found it rather unsung and underestimated
across the C++ community in comparison to other non-standard containers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, split into multiple parts, I will highlight all the benefits you can get using &lt;em&gt;boost::multi_index_container&lt;/em&gt; instead of the standard 
containers: faster, cleaner and simpler code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;multiple-views&quot;&gt;Multiple views&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You have a set of unique integers and do mainly two operations on it: &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;adding an integer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;iterating over the set in ascending and descending order&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is achievable quite easily with &lt;em&gt;boost::multi_index_container&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;namespace tags
{
struct asc {};
struct desc{};
}

using sorted_ints = boost::multi_index_container&amp;lt;
  int,                   // the stored object
  indexed_by&amp;lt;
    ordered_unique&amp;lt;      // first view
      tag&amp;lt;tags::asc&amp;gt;,    // tag used to access the view
      identity&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;,     // which part of the object is the key? the entire object.
      std::less&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;     // ascending order
    &amp;gt;,
    ordered_unique&amp;lt;      // second view
      tag&amp;lt;tags::desc&amp;gt;,   // its tag
      identity&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;,     // again, the key is the entire object
      std::greater&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;  // descending order
    &amp;gt;
  &amp;gt;
&amp;gt;;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/7519f9b37941626a673926e498317305.js?file=mic_ints_asc_desc.cpp&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The “hard” part done, the usage of the container itself is trivial. Actually, most of the operations are identical to the ones you can find on a standard container. The only
difference is that you have to get a &lt;em&gt;view&lt;/em&gt; on the container for some of the operations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sorted_ints mic;

// insert() and erase() can be performed directly on the container
mic.insert(2);
mic.insert(3);

auto&amp;amp;&amp;amp; view = mic.get&amp;lt;tags::asc&amp;gt;();
auto it = view.find(3);

mic.erase(it);

for (auto&amp;amp;&amp;amp; i : view)
  std::cout &amp;lt;&amp;lt; i &amp;lt;&amp;lt; std::endl;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/7519f9b37941626a673926e498317305.js?file=mic_view.cpp&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-unfortunate-alternative&quot;&gt;The unfortunate alternative&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alternative and unfortunately most common way to solve this problem is to maintain two &lt;em&gt;std::set&lt;/em&gt;, one using &lt;em&gt;std::greater&lt;/em&gt;, the other one &lt;em&gt;std::less&lt;/em&gt;. 
However, there are few problems with this approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is &lt;em&gt;error prone&lt;/em&gt;: each operation has to be done on the two sets, and if you forget you will have a bad time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;time efficiency&lt;/em&gt; is worse on insertion as you have the value twice — and even if the object is small it will be slower due to the memory allocations of the container&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;spatial efficiency&lt;/em&gt; will be worse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it can be &lt;em&gt;complicated&lt;/em&gt; if instead of storing twice the value you decide to store a pointer, reference or iterator in one of the two containers: they can be invalidated depending on the container and the operations performed on it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is not very &lt;em&gt;elegant&lt;/em&gt; from the code perspective&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if the constructor can throw, it will be even more fun, as you will have to handle exceptions properly and erase the previously inserted values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, yes, you can isolate the two containers in a separate &lt;em&gt;class&lt;/em&gt;, wrap all the methods, deal with the exceptions to 
rollback the operation if something throws and code the unit tests. Good luck, though! And it will be slower than Boost.MultiIndex,
and there will be another few hundreds of lines of code to maintain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performance&quot;&gt;Performance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we do C++, performance usually matters: how fast is this double-indexed &lt;em&gt;boost::multi_index_container&lt;/em&gt; compared to the two &lt;em&gt;std::set&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/speed_boost_multi_index_std_set.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Speed comparisons between boost::multi_index_container with two ordered indexes and two std::set, time in ms, measured on 1e6 iterations.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we thought, the &lt;em&gt;multi_index_container&lt;/em&gt; is much faster on insertion (and removal). The solution using two &lt;em&gt;std::set&lt;/em&gt;’s forces us to duplicate all the operations that modify the container: on insertion
and deletion, both sets need to be updated. This is especially bad as these operations involve memory allocations ; you can then expect this time difference to increase with the size of the value stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doing a lookup or walking in ascending or descending order, performance are almost the same — as they are done only on &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; std::set and not the two. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The entire code of this benchmark is available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/david-grs/boost_multi_index_container/blob/master/integers.cc&quot;&gt;my github&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see that the lookup is slightly slower, probably due to the overhead added by the multiple indexes. What can we do about that? Well, adding a third index, not &lt;em&gt;ordered&lt;/em&gt; this time, but &lt;em&gt;hashed&lt;/em&gt;! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;using sorted_ints = boost::multi_index_container&amp;lt;
  int,
  indexed_by&amp;lt;
    ordered_unique&amp;lt;
      tag&amp;lt;tags::asc&amp;gt;,
      identity&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;,
      std::less&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;
    &amp;gt;,
    ordered_unique&amp;lt;
      tag&amp;lt;tags::desc&amp;gt;,
      identity&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;,
      std::greater&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;
    &amp;gt;,
    hashed_unique&amp;lt;           // third view: unordered (hashed)
      tag&amp;lt;tags::unordered&amp;gt;,  // its tag
      identity&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;          // we hash the entire value
    &amp;gt;                        // no need to specify std::hash&amp;lt;int&amp;gt; here (it is the default parameter) 
  &amp;gt;
&amp;gt;;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/7519f9b37941626a673926e498317305.js?file=mic_ints_asc_desc_hashed.cpp&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
… and the lookup is now 10times faster. What is almost free with Boost.MultiIndex — adding an index — has definitely a cost in our alternative solution: if we add a &lt;em&gt;std::unorered_set&lt;/em&gt;,
the time of insertion and removal grows significantly (and the complexity of the code that manages this additional container too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/speed_boost_multi_index_std_set_and_unordered_set.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Speed comparisons between boost::multi_index_container with three indexes (two ordered, one hashed) and two std::set plus std::unordered_set, time in ms, measured on 1e6 iterations.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behind the scene, &lt;em&gt;boost::multi_index_container&lt;/em&gt; uses a system of headers in order to do its job. Each node consists in the stored object, plus a sequence of headers, depending on the indexes
that are used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a specific header for each index type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ordered&quot;&gt;Ordered&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ordered index is implemented as a red-black tree, thus the header is composed by 3 pointers: one to the parent and the two children pointers. An interesting point here is that the color of the node 
is — on most platforms — encoded in the LSB of the parent pointer, resulting in a header of 24 bytes instead of 32 bytes (on a 64-bit systems).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As none of the &lt;em&gt;std::map&lt;/em&gt; implementations I checked — libc++ and libstdc++ trunk (at the time of writing…) — performs such space optimization, this might explain the result we got in the previous 
benchmark, where the lookup was faster on  &lt;em&gt;boost::multi_index_container&lt;/em&gt; than &lt;em&gt;std::set&lt;/em&gt;. I actually don’t know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they don’t perform such optimization, if anybody knows, don’t hesitate to post a comment!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unordered&quot;&gt;Unordered&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implementation of the hash map requires two pointers for the bucket management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, &lt;em&gt;std::unordered_map&lt;/em&gt; (with GCC 6.2 on Linux x86-64) takes more space (3 pointers), which can explain why the lookup was ~20% slower. I didn’t dig into the code of &lt;em&gt;std::unordered_map&lt;/em&gt;, I only profiled its memory allocations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sequenced&quot;&gt;Sequenced&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sequenced index is implemented as a double-linked list: the header is composed by 2 pointers, one pointing to the next node, the other one to the previous node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;random-access&quot;&gt;Random access&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The random access index is implemented with an array of pointers to the nodes. In the node itself, the header is only composed by one pointer, which points back to its corresponding element in the main array of pointers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;index type&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;associated header           &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;size on 64-bit systems&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ordered&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3 pointers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24 bytes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;unordered (hashed)            &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2 pointers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16 bytes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;sequenced&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2 pointers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16 bytes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;random&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1 pointer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8 bytes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Then, in the previous double-ordered and hashed container, the overhead was &lt;em&gt;24+24+16=64 bytes&lt;/em&gt;. If we take &lt;em&gt;sizeof(int) == 4 bytes&lt;/em&gt;, each node takes &lt;em&gt;68 bytes&lt;/em&gt; in memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the other solution, each instance of &lt;em&gt;std::set&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;std::unordered_set&lt;/em&gt; uses &lt;em&gt;40 bytes&lt;/em&gt; (GCC 6.2, Linux, x86-64), resulting in a usage of &lt;em&gt;120 bytes&lt;/em&gt; per node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all for now! In a second part I will explain why Boost.MultiIndex can help you even if you don’t use multiple indexes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 21:47:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://david-grs.github.io/why_boost_multi_index_container-part1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://david-grs.github.io/why_boost_multi_index_container-part1</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>static_any: a low-latency stack-based Boost.Any</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When writing some speed-critical code, I wanted to use &lt;em&gt;Boost.Any&lt;/em&gt; as an attribute in a struct. This struct
was small — 2 cache lines — and I knew that all the types that I would store in this &lt;em&gt;Any&lt;/em&gt;
would fit in 16bytes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I thought “trivial, let’s use Boost.Any with a stack-based allocator”!&lt;br /&gt;
… and then I got disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disappointed, because &lt;em&gt;Boost.Any&lt;/em&gt; does not offer the possibility to use a custom allocator. To be honest, that would 
not have solved the story anyway, as &lt;em&gt;Boost.Any&lt;/em&gt; does other things that slow down this container, 
but that was enough to start thinking about another — home-made — solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Talk is cheap. Show me the code.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/david-grs/static_any&quot;&gt;static_any project on my github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;boostany-implementation&quot;&gt;Boost.Any implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why was &lt;em&gt;Boost.Any&lt;/em&gt; too slow in my case ? And why was I looking for a stack-based allocator ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Boost.Any&lt;/em&gt; is very simple: it erases the type via inheritance, and the few required operations, which are querying the type
and cloning the objects, are done via virtual methods. Here is a skeleton:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;  struct any
  {
      struct placeholder { ... };

      template &amp;lt;typename _T&amp;gt; 
      struct holder : public placeholder {  _T; ... }

      template &amp;lt;typename _T&amp;gt; 
      any(const _T&amp;amp; t) : m_placeholder(new holder&amp;lt;_T&amp;gt;(t)) {}

  private:
      holder* m_placeholder;
  };&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8b727b6d2e71361ffa730df4004b449c.js?file=boost_any_impl&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My main issue regarding this implementation was not at all with the costs of calling virtual methods, but with
the memory layout that this would imply to my structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that my stored types were small, and I wanted them on the same &lt;strong&gt;cache line&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be more concrete, let’s take the following code: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;  struct foo
  {
      int i;
      long l;
      boost::any a;
  };
  
  foo f;
  f.a = 1234;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8b727b6d2e71361ffa730df4004b449c.js?file=mem_layout&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The variables &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt; are next to each other in memory, but the integer &lt;em&gt;1234&lt;/em&gt; will be somewhere else — due to
the heap-based implementation of &lt;em&gt;Boost.Any&lt;/em&gt; — and maybe even on another page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, you get all the benefits when having these variables located in the same contiguous chunk of memory: better
data-locality means less memory cache misses and a better prefetching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-benchmark&quot;&gt;The benchmark&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always when talking about speed, we want to see some numbers. So here you are — it is in nanoseconds, the lower the better:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bench_any_boost_qvariant.png&quot; alt=&quot;Time spent on assignment and get operations in nanoseconds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason &lt;em&gt;static_any&lt;/em&gt; is faster on assignment is mainly due to the fact that is does not do a memory allocation. On the &lt;em&gt;get&lt;/em&gt; operation,
it is due to virtual calls and other implementation details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the main thing, the reason I wanted to have such generic container, i.e. a stack-based any, is not shown by these numbers. Because
when you benchmark a piece of code, you run this one in a loop, and you do not get any cache misses… These numbers are just for &lt;em&gt;raw
sppeed&lt;/em&gt; and most of the time, instructions per cycle for such operations won’t be your bottleneck, but memory can be one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;staticany&quot;&gt;static_any&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The usage is as simple as &lt;em&gt;Boost.Any&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;static_any&amp;lt;32&amp;gt; a = 1234;
int x = a.get&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;(); // returns 1234

bool bi = a.has&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;(); // returns true
bool bd = a.has&amp;lt;double&amp;gt;(); // returns false

double d = a.get&amp;lt;double&amp;gt;(); // throws!

a = std::string(&amp;quot;hello world&amp;quot;); // moved to a&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8b727b6d2e71361ffa730df4004b449c.js?file=static_any_example&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning, I only implemented it for trivially copyable types, as I was only using this container with such objects. This super simple 
and even faster container — but unsafe, as there is no type checking at runtime — is in the same header &lt;em&gt;any.hpp&lt;/em&gt; under the name 
of &lt;em&gt;static_any_t&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, after few discussions with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/maciekgajewski&quot;&gt;my workmate Maciek&lt;/a&gt;, he got the awesome idea about the &lt;em&gt;gateway function&lt;/em&gt;
that allows &lt;em&gt;static_any&lt;/em&gt; to go from the erased type — the vector of bytes that is used as underlying in &lt;em&gt;static_any&lt;/em&gt; — to the real
type T that is stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will describe that in a later post, meanwhile you can grab the code…&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:48:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://david-grs.github.io/low_latency_stack_based_boost_any</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://david-grs.github.io/low_latency_stack_based_boost_any</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>TLS performance overhead and cost on GNU/Linux</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When changing the implementation of a time clock, I had to switch from a static method — think about a classic
call to &lt;em&gt;clock_gettime()&lt;/em&gt; for example — to a per-thread model. Long story short, it was about a constant TSC that
was not so constant across different sockets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per-thread and static variables: that sounds like a perfect case for Thread-Local Storage (TLS). However this time clock
was widely used in my project and was taking so far a couple of CPU cycles, and I wanted to be sure that the TLS would not add
a significant overhead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick look on Google only revealed an article from the Intel Developer Zone: &lt;a href=&quot;https://software.intel.com/en-us/blogs/2011/05/02/the-hidden-performance-cost-of-accessing-thread-local-variables&quot;&gt;the hidden performance cost of accessing 
thread-local variables&lt;/a&gt;.
Among pro-tips like “you simply have to buy a Intel©® VTune™ licence and don’t forget the Parallel Studio XE©®™ it
only costs 2k$”, the awesome screenshots or the comment section where someone says that the code is slow due to the TLS 
implementation of Windows while another one points out the code was running under Linux, I simply decided to &lt;em&gt;figure out myself&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did what I prefer: I profiled it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h1 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you have &lt;strong&gt;statically linked&lt;/strong&gt; code, you can use a thread local variable like another one: there is only one TLS block and its
entire data is known at link-time, which allows the pre-calculation of all offsets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you are using &lt;strong&gt;dynamic modules&lt;/strong&gt;, there will be a lookup each time you access the thread local variable, but
you have some options in order to avoid it in speed-critical code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;micro-benchmarking-the-access-of-tls-data&quot;&gt;µ-benchmarking the access of TLS data&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a snippet that mimics the code I had in production: one was accessing a static variable, the other one a thread
local variable, through a static method of the class. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;#pragma once

struct Inc
{
    void operator()();
    static int m_counter;
};

struct IncTLS
{
    void operator()();
    static thread_local int m_counter;
};&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=inc.hpp&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;#include &amp;quot;inc.hpp&amp;quot;

int Inc::m_counter = 0;
thread_local int IncTLS::m_counter = 0;

void Inc::operator()()    { ++m_counter; }
void IncTLS::operator()() { ++m_counter; }&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=inc.cpp&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Note that the &lt;em&gt;thread_local&lt;/em&gt; keyword was introduced in C++11, and implemented in GCC 4.8 or newer. If you are using an older version, you can use the &lt;em&gt;__thread&lt;/em&gt; GCC keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To time my experiments,  I am using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/david-grs/geiger&quot; title=&quot;Geiger, a benchmarking library in C++&quot;&gt;geiger&lt;/a&gt;, a benchmarking library I developed. 
geiger can read &lt;a href=&quot;https://perf.wiki.kernel.org/index.php/Main_Page&quot; title=&quot;Profiling hardware counters&quot;&gt;hardware performance counters&lt;/a&gt; — using the PAPI library — 
and is ideal to benchmark very short snippets of code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I simply declare a benchmark suite with two tests. The first one accesses static data, and the second one thread local data. The suite is run twice: the first time, each test is run once, 
and the second time, each test is run one hundred times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;#include &amp;quot;inc.hpp&amp;quot;

#include &amp;lt;geiger/benchmark.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;vector&amp;gt;

int main(int argc, char **argv)
{
    geiger::init();
    geiger::suite&amp;lt;geiger::instr_profiler&amp;gt; s;

    Inc inc;
    IncTLS inc_tls;

    s.add(&amp;quot;static&amp;quot;, [&amp;amp;]()
          {
              inc();
          });

    s.add(&amp;quot;tls&amp;quot;, [&amp;amp;]()
          {
              inc_tls();
          });

    s.set_printer&amp;lt;geiger::printers::console&amp;gt;();
    s.run(1);
    s.run(100);

    return 0;
}&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=tls.cpp&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Let’s build it with our favorite flags:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;cmake_minimum_required(VERSION 2.8)

set(CMAKE_CXX_FLAGS &amp;quot;${CMAKE_CXX_FLAGS} -Wall -g -O3 std=c++14&amp;quot;)

add_executable(tls tls.cpp inc.cpp)
target_link_libraries(tls geiger)&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=CMakelists.txt&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The results are quite straightforward: no overhead at all. There is always a bit of jitter with hardware counters, so do not 
conclude we have more cycles with the TLS test, there is quite some variance here between several runs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;Test      Time (ns)   PAPI_TOT_INS    PAPI_TOT_CYC   PAPI_BR_MSP
----------------------------------------------------------------
static            4            994           1,699            12
tls               4            994           1,812            10&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=Output.txt&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The assembly code also confirms it. I build with CLang 3.6 but I got the same with GCC 4.7:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;$ disass ./tls &amp;quot;Inc::operator()()&amp;quot;
Dump of assembler code for function Inc::operator()():
   0x0000000000404f40 &amp;lt;+0&amp;gt;:     inc    DWORD PTR [rip+0x202382]
   0x0000000000404f46 &amp;lt;+6&amp;gt;:     ret    
End of assembler dump.

$ disass ./tls &amp;quot;IncTLS::operator()()&amp;quot;
Dump of assembler code for function IncTLS::operator()():
   0x0000000000404f50 &amp;lt;+0&amp;gt;:     inc    DWORD PTR fs:0xfffffffffffffffc
   0x0000000000404f58 &amp;lt;+8&amp;gt;:     ret    
End of assembler dump.&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=Assembly.txt&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;NB&lt;/strong&gt;: the glibc is using the segment register FS for accessing the TLS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-about-tlsgetaddr-&quot;&gt;How about __tls_get_addr ?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, all is good, I can use TLS as I want. But hang on… how about this function that was in the callstack on the 
Intel blog, &lt;em&gt;__tls_get_addr&lt;/em&gt; ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One thing that always scares me the most when I do micro benchmarks is about the reliability of their results. Indeed, it 
is very easy to screw up. You have to generate some &lt;em&gt;realistic&lt;/em&gt; inputs that will trigger the same behavior that you got
in production, without too many side effects. And from the D-cache to the BTB, everything is hot…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we have a sneaky case: the compilation is part of the environment of our benchmark. If the thread variable is in a dynamic
module, the linker cannot compute a direct reference to it and we get the much vaunted lookup!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s build it again, as a shared library this time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;cmake_minimum_required(VERSION 2.8)

set(CMAKE_CXX_FLAGS &amp;quot;${CMAKE_CXX_FLAGS} -Wall -g -O3 std=c++14&amp;quot;)

add_library(inc SHARED inc.cpp)
add_executable(tls tls.cpp)
target_link_libraries(tls inc geiger)&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=CMakelists_shared.txt&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There is in this case a difference ; the method that accesses the thread local variable takes twice more time. Please not that 
this overhead is still very small, as in this case we compare it to an extremely cheap operation…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;Test      Time (ns)   PAPI_TOT_INS    PAPI_TOT_CYC   PAPI_BR_MSP
----------------------------------------------------------------
static            6          1,194           2,990            20
tls              12          2,694           3,568            15&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=Output2.txt&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The assembly code shows the same difference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;$ disass ./libinc.so &amp;quot;Inc::operator()()&amp;quot;
Dump of assembler code for function Inc::operator()():
   0x0000000000000870 &amp;lt;+0&amp;gt;:     mov    rax,QWORD PTR [rip+0x200781]
   0x0000000000000877 &amp;lt;+7&amp;gt;:     inc    DWORD PTR [rax]
   0x0000000000000879 &amp;lt;+9&amp;gt;:     ret    
End of assembler dump.

$ disass ./libinc.so &amp;quot;IncTLS::operator()()&amp;quot;
Dump of assembler code for function IncTLS::operator()():
   0x0000000000000880 &amp;lt;+0&amp;gt;:     push   rax
   0x0000000000000881 &amp;lt;+1&amp;gt;:     data32 lea rdi,[rip+0x20074f]
   0x0000000000000889 &amp;lt;+9&amp;gt;:     data32 data32 call 0x770 &amp;lt;__tls_get_addr@plt&amp;gt;
   0x0000000000000891 &amp;lt;+17&amp;gt;:    inc    DWORD PTR [rax]
   0x0000000000000893 &amp;lt;+19&amp;gt;:    pop    rax
   0x0000000000000894 &amp;lt;+20&amp;gt;:    ret    
End of assembler dump.&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=Assembly2.txt&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-tls-implementation-in-elf&quot;&gt;The TLS implementation in ELF&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As global and static variables are stored in &lt;em&gt;.data&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;.bss&lt;/em&gt; sections, thread local variables get stored in equivalent 
&lt;em&gt;.tdata&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;.tbss&lt;/em&gt; sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each thread has its on TCB — &lt;em&gt;Thread Control Block&lt;/em&gt; — that contains some metadata about the thread itself. One
metadata is the address of the DTV — Dynamic Thread Vector — which is a vector that contains pointers to 
thread local variables and other TLS blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tls_implementation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;TLS implementation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using statically linked code, everything is simpler as there is &lt;strong&gt;only one TLS block&lt;/strong&gt;. As the offsets to the thread local
variables are known at link-time, the compiler is able to generate a direct access to the thread local variable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you have dynamic modules, several TLS blocks are present. It is easier to see with the following simplified version 
of &lt;em&gt;__tls_get_addr&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;offset&lt;/em&gt; is known at build time, then &lt;em&gt;module_id&lt;/em&gt; is the only variable, which is zero when using static
linking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;void* __tls_get_offset(size_t module_id, size_t offset)
{
    char* tls_block = dtv[thread_id][module_id];
    
    if (tls_block == UNALLOCATED_TLS_BLOCK)
        tls_block = dtv[thread_id][module_id] = allocate_tls(module_id);
    
    return tls_block + offset;
}&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=tls_get_offset.c&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is the actual implementation from the glibc 2.20:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;void *
__tls_get_addr (GET_ADDR_ARGS)
{
  dtv_t *dtv = THREAD_DTV (); 

  if (__glibc_unlikely (dtv[0].counter != GL(dl_tls_generation)))
    return update_get_addr (GET_ADDR_PARAM);

  void *p = dtv[GET_ADDR_MODULE].pointer.val;

  if (__glibc_unlikely (p == TLS_DTV_UNALLOCATED))
    return tls_get_addr_tail (GET_ADDR_PARAM, dtv, NULL);

  return (char *) p + GET_ADDR_OFFSET;
}&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=dl-tls.c&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The ABI specific parts are implemented in sysdeps ; as for x86_64, we access the TCB from the segment register FS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;/* Return the address of the dtv for the current thread.  */
# define THREAD_DTV() \
  ({ struct pthread *__pd;                                                    \
     THREAD_GETMEM (__pd, header.dtv); })


/* Read member of the thread descriptor directly.  */
# define THREAD_GETMEM(descr, member) \
  ({ __typeof (descr-&amp;gt;member) __value;                                        \
     if (sizeof (__value) == 1)                                               \
       asm volatile (&amp;quot;movb %%fs:%P2,%b0&amp;quot;                                      \
                     : &amp;quot;=q&amp;quot; (__value)                                         \
                     : &amp;quot;0&amp;quot; (0), &amp;quot;i&amp;quot; (offsetof (struct pthread, member)));     \
      ....
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/david-grs/8f8f38b6b63216a97c5c.js?file=x86_64_tls.h&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So what?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessing thread local variables is cheap in both cases ; the lookup done by the glibc is very fast (and takes a constant time). 
But if your code is — or could be — loaded as a dynamic module and is speed-critical, then it can be worth spending
some time to &lt;strong&gt;avoid this lookup&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One easy win could be to access the thread local data from the same block of code. The compiler will be smart enough to call only
once &lt;em&gt;__tls_get_addr&lt;/em&gt;. This could be done by, for example, &lt;strong&gt;inlining&lt;/strong&gt; the function that access the TLS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could think about &lt;em&gt;keeping the reference&lt;/em&gt; of the thread local variable, but I found this solution very dodgy. You might have to prepare your arguments to pass the code review :) …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information about the TLS and its implementation on GNU/Linux in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.akkadia.org/drepper/tls.pdf&quot; title=&quot;ELF Handling for TLS from Ulrich Drepper&quot;&gt;ELF Handling for TLS&lt;/a&gt; from Ulrich Drepper.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 19:03:20 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://david-grs.github.io/tls_performance_overhead_cost_linux</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://david-grs.github.io/tls_performance_overhead_cost_linux</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
